If you look at the history of the industry, the open source version of everything has been much safer. So the internet and Linux were far safer than Windows, like by our lot. The safest thing for the world is that there's not one AI to rule them all, that there's AI for everybody. And I think that open source is basically the best path towards that goal.
It's probably the single most important policy issue around AI. It feels like we're at a stable equilibrium in the market, but the truth is the AI market is probably less than 3% penetrated. Should AI be open? Theo Jaffe and Sofia Puccini are joined by Ben Horowitz to discuss the battle over open source AI. Why he believes open models are essential to innovation and national security.
And with the future of AI competition means for startups, frontier labs, and the broader technology ecosystem. We are live with Ben Horowitz of Andreessen Horowitz who needs no introduction. So we'll just dive right into it. Ben, welcome back to MTS. Thank you, thank you. Happy to be here. So, so much has happened in the world of open source, open weights in the last couple of weeks. It's gotten, you know, it's gotten real.
There's there's some drama going on. There's an open letter released by Nvidia today called open weights in American AI leadership signed by many companies including Andrews and Horowitz. So can you tell us a little bit about the intent behind this letter and what you hope to achieve from it? Yeah, so I think that it's it's probably the single most important policy issue around AI That's kind of currently going on
And the kind of battle is between kind of almost an anti-competitive stance, guised in a kind of safety cloak, is kind of what we ought to be doing. And so if you look at why is open source important, and there's many reasons. The first will just start.
like academia is completely out of the AI game if there's no open source. So like that goes away. I think secondly, we just had a really interesting security incident with open AI hacking into Hugging Face. And the only way Hugging Face was able to prevent it, because the proprietary model said guardrails, which prevented them from doing security tasks, was to use an open source model.
And I think the important point there is you can't actually ban open source, of course. It's out there. It's a file. It's on the internet. We have no way of doing that. And it reminds me of years ago when I was at Netscape, they tried to ban cryptography. And the math is out there. You're not going to ban it. It's not actually possible. But you can prevent the good guys from using it.
And that's what would happen, I think, in the case of an open source ban is, you know, the threats would be, well, you can't work with the US government if you use open source or you can't do this. So a company like Huggingface would not be able to actually use the product. So that, you know, would be bad. But then kind of getting into just like the, if you look at the history of the industry, the open source version of everything has been much safer. So the internet.
and Linux were far safer than Windows, like by our lot. And why is that? Well, because the whole community could work on the safety problems, as opposed to just a company and particularly a monopoly company that, you know, like you can't, even if Windows has a million security bugs, there's nothing we can do about it because it was a monopoly at the time. And so that, you know, that's a very difficult position for the world to be in.
If you look at now the argument against open AI or AI being open source is, oh, well, nobody understands how the weights work. So, you know, it's not like people could inspect it. But why is it better to not see the weights if that's the case? And I think in reality, if you look at the really tough problems that we have safety wise, the toughest being reward hacking.
currently and obviously Anthropoc has not solved it. Obviously OpenAI has not solved it because we just had these incidents. Well, should the whole world be able to look at, okay, how are the weights moving? Why is it that guardrails don't prevent the reward hack? And maybe somebody can come up with an answer. Somebody who doesn't work for one of the proprietary labs who are much more focused on, you know, obviously keeping ahead on the benchmarks and
getting the money and all that kind of thing, you know, what if the whole community could work on it? So it's like really, really important, I think, to safety in general. And then, you know, kind of finally, the safest thing for the world is that there's not one AI to rule them all, that there's kind of AI for everybody. And I think that open source is basically the best path, you know, kind of towards that goal. Right. So Jensen.
made a Twitter account basically to publish this. Good for Jensen. Right? So that I think speaks to the significance of where we are right now that he was like, okay, it now is the time to speak out about this and get all these companies to like, you know, co-sign it. What do you think are some of the risks right now from like a government action perspective on open source? Well, look, I think there's a huge push with a lot of money behind it.
particularly from anthropocte to ban open source. I think that it is kind of nefarious from my point of view, but whatever their motivation is, they do have, so one of the things that happened with cryptography is there are people who are very senior in the intelligence community who didn't understand the technological aspect of it.
who push for banning cryptography because they wanted control. And I think that it's a similar thing here where it just feels like more control if you can stop some kind of AI. But those are very powerful forces in the conversation right now. And I think that there is certainly a kind of pretty strong community pushing for the banning of the...
of open source. And so that's why this letter was so important to I had so great that, you know, not just Jensen, but Elon, Satya, Sam all supported it. And I think it's, I just think it's very obviously the right answer for safety, the right answer for America. And it would be a real shame if we, you know, kind of shot ourselves and to put on this. Yeah.
Well, another angle that many people talk about with respect to open source is China and national security, as opposed to like AI safety stuff. And some people say, you know, it's a national security risk for so many American startups to be dependent on like infrastructure that comes from China, you know, in the event that, for example, China decided to cut everything off and stop releasing better open source models to American companies.
or perhaps they could, you know, in an AI future, make these open source models like sleeper agents basically. Or you can think of all kinds of things that they could do. Yeah, I mean, as could write a Chinese national working for Anthropica or open AI or, you know, SpaceX, right? Like it's not like these Chinese nationals cannot be
activated by the Chinese government. Like we've seen that. So like if that's a threat, like I think that's just a general threat, not specific to open source AI. And then nothing against Chinese nationals. We love them. They're great for our country and so forth. But like if you're worried about that, you know, you ought to be worried about it. Like the more likely way I think would be that kind of spy activation. But like it's open source. And so
If they stop making it like we've still got the last codebase we can train up to model. We can learn from it. Meanwhile, there's, I mean, the great thing about Open is it's open. And look, we need to build our own open source products here. Thinking Machines is doing a good job of that. I think in France, you know, Mistral is doing a good job of that. So like we need to keep pushing the technology forward, the open technology.
So that it, look, it needs to be available everywhere for everyone. Like we can't be held hostage by, like the worst scenario is there ends up being a monopoly in AI. I mean, I think it's fairly obvious how dangerous that could be and how powerful that company would be and what a national security risk that would be. We've already seen a glimpse of it right with Amphropoc saying like, I don't care who got elected in the U.S. I don't care about the government. I don't care about the Department of War.
We're not going to work with you. We're in charge. And so you look at that, you go, okay, that seems like a much bigger national security risk than the kinds of little holes people are trying to poke in the open source story. So I just think it's very, very important that this technology proliferate and not be kept contained in a single company. Yeah, definitely. So we have like a
kind of become a little more defenders of distillation recently. So we talk about how, you know, like distillation is not actually like illegal. Like a lot of the labs are still paying API prices.
to use the models. So what are your thoughts? Do you think it's part of a healthy competitive plan? We talked to Aaron Levy earlier about this and he was like, how can Anthropic just take everyone's training data without paying them at all, but when other labs pay them, it's distillation. It needs to be banned.
Yeah, I actually agree with Aaron and I think that's right like from a legal standpoint There is the outputs of AI models are not copyright and they don't fall under copyright law So the only thing it could be is the terms of service violation But luck I think generally that's right, you know anthropic just paid 1.5 billion dollars for stealing everybody's books including mine better they trained on my book and I joined that class action lawsuit so
You know, not to say, look, I'm for training the model, building a statistical model of the things we know. I think that's generally good for the world. And so far at this line is, you know, violate the copyright and reproduce the original work. And I think the same, yeah, like I think distillation is generally good for the world. I also think they're going to have a very hard time stopping it for many reasons. Yeah, they have theories on how they're going to stop it, but I'm not sure that those are going to succeed. So we'll see.
But yeah, I think this relation is good and like the whole idea that we're stealing American stuff. By the way, the data companies are all out selling to everybody, you know, including the Chinese companies that are building these things. So, you know, I don't know how much you can contain all this stuff anyway.
So why do you think that so far over the last few years Chinese labs have surpassed American labs in terms of open source performance? Well, because I think that all the American labs have kind of built their businesses on proprietary models and there's a lot kind of that becomes and they have to to kind of afford the GPUs You know, they need these very high valuations to keep ahead on the GPUs to keep going
And because they're in the lead, distillation doesn't work for them because their model is on the cutting edge, it's on the frontier. And that's just how kind of the markets evolved. I think, generally that's been the way it is. Like the number one is never opened. And then number two goes open is kind of the history of the software industry.
I do think that we're going to see, I mean, like I said, with thinking machines, they've got, you know, they're making really good headway with their open source efforts. So, you know, hopefully we'll see kind of more of that and kind of more breakthroughs, you know, on the open source side. But like part of the challenge or part of the reason why AI is just so different than software is you can throw money at the problem, right? Like so, if you have more GPUs, that's actually turns out to be a really big deal.
Yeah, what about open source in industries like robotics because like unitary is at least like You know a large percentage open source and it looks like you know like they have just had like such a you know booming industry and like so much deployment within China and we don't have anything like that here Do you think that we're missing like that you open source ecosystem in the US?
Or is it just a different thing? I mean, there's obviously supply chain and stuff. No, I think there's a lot to be said for that, right? Because, you know, as an application, so what's happened, the other thing that we haven't spoken about, like is, well, what's the AI platform? And, you know, so if you're an application provider, what do you build on? And what we've seen is it's been already
fairly dangerous to build on Amprapaq because they every time an application category starts to do well, they move into that category. And then they've, you know, like we've seen them do like very aggressive things where, you know, the price for the application provider is full price and then they subsidize their version of the application. And so it's a kind of that
Did they kind of fast forwarded, I would say, the Microsoft Playbook from the old days to like skipping the platform generation and just going straight to the monopoly generation? And so if you're an application provider, like, okay, how can I safely build on a proprietary model if that company is going to come attack me and then charge me much more than they're charging themselves to do the same thing?
And so open source is kind of a way that the ecosystem gets built. So if you're building robots, for example, if you were to build your robot on AmphiRocket, then at some point, you know AmphiRocket is going to go into the robot business and put you out of business just by either cutting you off or overcharging you. And so this is kind of a way that their ecosystem can grow by building on the open source. And hopefully, look, by the way, a lot of our industry has grown. A lot of our application companies
have used open source to kind of bootstrap themselves or get going or that kind of thing. And often Chinese open source, which is why, you know, it's really important to the US ecosystem that we have applications that we have embodied AI that we have robots and all these things that we have access to that technology because the kind of other model is a monopoly model where there's one company that owns all the applications and all the robots and all of everything.
And look, I'm not even mad at them for doing that. Necessarily, it's their business approach, but the consequences of it, if they're able to ban their competitors is not good. Yeah, I also worry about these very monopolistic centralized futures. And one area in particular that I think might be concerning in the future is if one AI company is able to use its AIs to
Automated to a research process and then become much more capable than everyone else very quickly It seems like you know that wouldn't be so good for like a pluralistic, you know startup ecosystem So yeah, that's certainly their strategy, you know and we'll see how it goes But I think that kind of the best hedge against that is for like many many companies being able to do AI which is why the open models are powerful in that context Yeah, I guess speaking of China
There's a lot of things that are either like tariffed or I mean we export control, we also tariff them. Things like EVs, right? We talk about EVs all the time. And if we had like a BYD level pricing for EVs in the US that would just be like so huge. Do you think there's a way that we could move towards that future? What would it take to get to that? Well I think that...
You know with BYD in particular there are a lot of subsidies from the Chinese government that enabled them to achieve this amazing pricing and a lot of it is a kind of a well, so kind of getting into manufacturing and you know the US is so we as a country kind of invented So much of manufacturing and then kind of forgot what we knew
So like if you go back to, we won World War II based on our superior manufacturing capability. And then like over the next whatever 100 years we forgot to hold that. We need to rebuild that capability and manufacturing has changed and is becoming much more automated, much more kind of AI centric. And so I think as we kind of build into the second, or you call it the third industrial revolution,
that being able to be competitive on manufacturing by building automated factories and so forth, similar to what Elon has been able to do at Tesla and in the Gigafactory and so forth is gonna be the way that we get to competitiveness there for sure. Yeah, definitely. Yeah. What other open source companies with regards to AI? No, we have like...
A16Z portco thinking machines. Yeah, but you know where else and Mistral yeah, yeah Where else do you see like new open-source models coming out of would it require literally just like a Gates foundation? Yeah, there's not a lot of coming out in America right now, but you know and
But I think it can happen. And then there are some real efforts in academia. My friend, Jan Stoika from Berkeley is kind of working hard to put together a project where we can fund kind of open source model in that everybody in academia can use and build on. And I think that's just really important. If you look at the history of technology in this country, a lot of it kind of starts in universities.
I hadn't been iced out of AI due to the incredible cost and the threat that open source is under. And well, a lack of US open source in particular. In the long run, what exactly is the incentive for a business to release open source models, especially at their foundation lab and most of their businesses making the models which are very expensive?
Yeah, so I think that I mean this is where like I'm glad you both are pro distillation Because I think that's important equation, but look I think that there's a there's different business like I think the business model of Selling serving the model out of very high premium doesn't work if you're open source, but there's other things You know particularly luck one of the things we already know is that you know for an enterprise and a B2B context
a really well post-trained kind of less powerful smaller model works often better for a business task than like a large, you know, kind of a large proprietary model and as much cheaper as well. So cheaper, faster and get to their answer. So I think that it would be more like a kind of a Palantir looking business model than it would be a anthropoplastic business model.
and then, you know, true also on the consumer side, you know, we've seen on consumer like the use case really, really matters. And so kind of tuning a model for that kind of thing can really work.
open source models are currently a threat to the business model of large closed source foundation model developers. Like I can imagine yes, because if people can get similar capabilities for a much lower price point, they'd switch over. But also like when you compare Kimmy to Fable or Sol, there's definitely areas where Fable and Sol are just way better and people will pay for them anyway. Yeah, I don't think anybody's a threat, a real kind of current threat to anybody else's business right now. Like
in that we're so early in the market. So the thing that's very deceptive about AI is because the market is so much larger than any other market we've seen prior, that it feels like, okay, we're kind of at a stable equilibrium in the market. But the truth is, the AI market is probably less than 3% penetrated. And so everybody's gonna grow.
Right like when deep-seek came out. It was a deep-seek moment and oh my gosh, and this is the end of anthropocon open AI and all that and Nothing changed Right like nothing changed zero and that's because but deep-seek is more valuable and Anthropocon's more valuable and open AI is more valuable You know they all agree and this space X is more valuable. So I Think that at this stage of the market everything is going to grow a lot and nobody's gonna pounce on
other people's market share in a way that is so material that it's gonna like cripple them. Yeah. Now, at some day, when we get to some kind of equilibria in the market and there's so much share to go around and then you're fighting each other for share, then these things may come into play, but for right now, I don't think so. Yeah, the pie overall is so big. I wonder if this follows also for like- Yeah, it's like the biggest pie of all time. Yeah.
when would we have some indication of the AI market is actually settling to an equilibrium? We can't really rely on historical data because this is sort of an unprecedented technology. Yeah, I think it's pretty hard to see because everybody who's using it keeps using it more and more and more and more. You talk to businesses and they're kind of token usages.
grow them like 10-fold annually. But I think we'll see it when you kind of see growth really slow down in the various players and things like that. But the slangs thing are growing like several, a thousand percent a year, 500 percent a year. We're nowhere near to that state. And stable markets things grow like whatever.
What companies do you see are currently benefiting the most from very, very cheap intelligence? Like the kind of companies that use the Kimmys and the deep seeks. Yeah, that's a good question. I mean, I think that, you know, a lot of software companies are able to use it for various tasks. I think on the things like customer support and specialized applications, people are able to benefit a lot from them.
And then, you know, look, I think cursor survived for a long time because it was able to have an open source alternative for cheap tasks that they have. And, you know, now they're, of course, they're on, they're on GROC. But, you know, I think every application company in AI world benefits from open source right now to some degree, like they're all using some, nobody's not using an open source model who's an application provider.
that I know of. So it's kind of that whole field. And so it's really a catastrophe for that whole part of the ecosystem if these guys get their way. Yeah, it comes to these like very cheap models. It seems like I can imagine a future where if the really good models like the flagship frontier models get much more capable.
and can really do a lot of the tasks that an employee can do at a job that enterprises would be gladly willing to spend a lot more on that rather than go to the much cheaper models in order to cut costs. So do you think that could... I think that's been the case so far, right? So it's not like anthropists having trouble selling fable or open AI's having trouble selling soul. Those things are growing very fast.
Brian very fast. So I think that's true. And then there's a question about which categories of jobs would you rather have super intelligence and pay 8x or 10x as much for and then which class of jobs would you rather have something faster and cheaper? And that'll be a question. And I think there's probably plenty of jobs in each category, just like the humans, right?
Would you pay a crazy amount of money for an AI researcher? Oh, definitely, like clearly. And then there's, okay, would you pay an insane amount of money for a janitorial service? And probably, you know, like would you pay 100X for a better janitor? Maybe not. Would you pay 100X more for a better accountant? I don't think so. Yeah.
So like so there there's different jobs in different categories So, you know not everything will be that but there will be plenty of jobs that are that Another question. It's kind of random, but how optimistic are you about AI art? Do you like do you think how do you think we're gonna fix the slot problem? Do you think it's gonna get worse before it gets better? No, I think it'll
The way I would look at it is I'm not that worried about the slap problem. I think that I Think the exciting thing is that for creatives any idea you have is now possible and so we're gonna get a lot of new ideas bright new ideas and everything in our film music You know new kinds of things that you know new kinds of video ideas and so far so I think it's gonna be
a little bit of a renaissance for it in that like every time we have a new technology we get new kinds of art. And you know, from like the invention of the saxophone, which I think was like in 1800s, 1850 or something like that, the invention of electric guitar, you know, we got rock and roll from that. We got jazz from the.
invention of the saxophone and we got hip-hop from the invention of the drum machine. Like every time there's a new technology, we get a new kind of art form in music and I think that's gonna happen here. And there will be stuff that's really good and there will be more people who can make bad things. There was more people who could be bad rappers than there were who could be bad rock and roll. You don't have to play an instrument. But that's okay. Like I think that's fine. I'm for that.
Like, you know, anything that... I also think it's just good for everybody to be able to express themselves. And so better tools for expression is generally a good thing, you know? There are issues with it. You know, I do get nostalgic for some of the things of the past, of course, but, you know, like, I'm certainly... What music are you listening to now? Yeah, so it's been a little bit of a drought for me on new music, but...
I actually liked that new though, Wyclef album. I thought it was pretty interesting that he just did. And I've probably been listening to a lot of old music. I've been listening to Curtis Mayfields who is really underrated, really good. Yeah. I think like with things like this, it increases the amount of like really mediocre artists, not mediocre because that's mean, but like, yeah. And then it makes it really hard to be very, very good.
Just because there's so much competition in the space and everyone is like it's like very democratized Which is a good thing, but it's just hard for like from a discernment perspective kind of Yeah, but that kind of happened in a big way with Spotify too, right? Yeah SoundCloud SoundCloud anybody could put anything on their YouTube all that kind of thing But you know I still think there's
There's great stuff that's higher art and there is, and there will continue to be, I can't get it. Yeah, I totally agree. Well, Ben has been so great having you on MTS. Talk about opening. Thanks for joining us and music. Thanks so much for joining. Yeah. Okay, thanks a lot and appreciate it very much. Thanks for that. Thanks for listening to this episode of the A16Z podcast. If you liked this episode, be sure to like, comment, subscribe, leave us a rating or review.
and share it with your friends and family. For more episodes, go to YouTube, Apple Podcasts, and Spotify. Follow us on X and A16Z and subscribe to our sub-stack at a16z.substack.com. Thanks again for listening and I'll see you in the next episode. This information is for educational purposes only and is not a recommendation to buy, hold, or sell any investment or financial product.
This podcast has been produced by a third party and may include pay promotional advertisements, other company references, and individuals unaffiliated with A16Z. Such advertisements, companies, and individuals are not endorsed by AH Capital Management LLC, A16Z, or any of its affiliates. Information is from sources deemed reliable on the data publication, but A16Z does not guarantee its accuracy.